<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Matteo Croci</title>
    <link>https://croci.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Matteo Croci</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://croci.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;university-of-the-basque-country-upvehu-bilbao-spain&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of the Basque Country (UPV/EHU), Bilbao, Spain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;2024-2025&#34;&gt;2024-2025&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lecturer in High-Performance Computing for Artificial Intelligence for the specialization course (“titulo proprio”) in Applied Artificial Intelligence and its Mathematical Foundations.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mathematical-institute-university-of-oxford-oxford-uk&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mathematical Institute, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;2020-2021&#34;&gt;2020-2021&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lecturer for the MATLAB course for the MSc in Mathematical Modelling and Scientific Computing.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tutor for the Simulation Methods and Stochastic Algorithms course for the Mathematics of Random System CDT.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;2019-2020&#34;&gt;2019-2020&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tutor for the Simulation Methods and Stochastic Algorithms course for the Mathematics of Random System CDT.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tutor for the M6 course on numerical methods for the MSc in Mathematical and Computational Finance.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;2018-2019&#34;&gt;2018-2019&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Head demonstrator for the Computational Mathematics course.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;2017-2018&#34;&gt;2017-2018&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tutor in Continuous Mathematics for Balliol and Wadham Colleges.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Demonstrator for the Computational Mathematics course.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Assistant Tutor for the MSc in Mathematical and Computational Finance Monte Carlo Methods course.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;2016-2017&#34;&gt;2016-2017&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;TA in Practical Numerical Analysis for the MSc in Mathematical Modelling and Scientific Computing.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tutor in Lincoln College for the B6.2 Numerical Solutions of Differential Equations II course.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;TA in B6.2 Numerical Solutions of Differential Equations II.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Demonstrator for the Computational Mathematics course.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/level_set2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/level_set2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-a-l-haji-ali-i-c-j-powell--preprint&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, A.-L. Haji-Ali, I. C. J. Powell, &lt;em&gt;An adaptive sampling algorithm for level-set approximation&lt;/em&gt;, Preprint (2025).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14896&#34;&gt;Preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We propose a new numerical scheme for approximating level-sets of Lipschitz&#xA;multivariate functions which is robust to stochastic noise. The algorithm&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;main feature is an adaptive grid-based stochastic approximation strategy which&#xA;automatically refines the approximation over regions close to the level set.&#xA;This strategy combines a local function approximation method with a noise&#xA;reduction scheme and produces $\varepsilon$-accurate approximations with an&#xA;expected cost complexity reduction of $\varepsilon^{-(p+1)/(\alpha p)}$&#xA;compared to a non-adaptive scheme, where $\alpha$ is the convergence rate of&#xA;the function approximation method and we assume that the noise can be&#xA;controlled in $L^p$. We provide numerical experiments in support of our&#xA;theoretical findings. These include 2- and 3-dimensional functions with a&#xA;complex level set structure, as well as a failure region estimation problem&#xA;described by a hyperelasticity partial differential equation with random field&#xA;coefficients.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/mpfem_preprint_2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/mpfem_preprint_2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-g-n-wells--preprint-software&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, G. N. Wells, &lt;em&gt;Mixed-precision finite element kernels and assembly: Rounding error analysis and hardware acceleration&lt;/em&gt;, Preprint (2024).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12614&#34;&gt;Preprint&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/croci/mpfem-paper-experiments-2024&#34;&gt;Software&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this paper we develop the first fine-grained rounding error analysis of finite element (FE) cell kernels and assembly. The theory includes mixed-precision implementations and accounts for hardware-acceleration via matrix multiplication units, thus providing theoretical guidance for designing reduced- and mixed-precision FE algorithms on CPUs and GPUs.  Guided by this analysis, we introduce hardware-accelerated mixed-precision implementation strategies which are provably robust to low-precision computations. Indeed, these algorithms are accurate to the lower-precision unit roundoff with an error constant that is independent from: the conditioning of FE basis function evaluations, the ill-posedness of the cell, the polynomial degree, and the number of quadrature nodes.  Consequently, we present the first AMX-accelerated FE kernel implementations on Intel Sapphire Rapids CPUs.  Numerical experiments demonstrate that the proposed mixed- (single/half-) precision algorithms are up to 60 times faster than their double precision equivalent while being orders of magnitude more accurate than their fully half-precision counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/mlblue_2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/mlblue_2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-k-e-willcox-s-j-wright--article-software&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, K. E. Willcox, S. J. Wright, &lt;em&gt;Multi-output multilevel best linear unbiased estimators via semidefinite programming&lt;/em&gt;, Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering (2023).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cma.2023.116130&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/croci/bluest&#34;&gt;Software&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Multifidelity forward uncertainty quantification (UQ) problems often involve multiple quantities of interest and heterogeneous models (e.g., different grids, equations, dimensions, physics, surrogate and reduced-order models). While computational efficiency is key in this context, multi-output strategies in multilevel/multifidelity methods are either sub-optimal or non-existent. In this paper we extend multilevel best linear unbiased estimators (MLBLUE) to multi-output forward UQ problems and we present new semidefinite programming formulations for their optimal setup. Not only do these formulations yield the optimal number of samples required, but also the optimal selection of low-fidelity models to use. While existing MLBLUE approaches are single-output only and require a non-trivial nonlinear optimization procedure, the new multi-output formulations can be solved reliably and efficiently. We demonstrate the efficacy of the new methods and formulations in practical UQ problems with model heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/mprkc_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/mprkc_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-g-rosilho-de-souza--article-slides&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, G. Rosilho de Souza, &lt;em&gt;Mixed-precision explicit stabilized Runge-Kutta methods for single- and multi-scale differential equations&lt;/em&gt;, Journal of Computational Physics (2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcp.2022.111349&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/NAseminar21-06-01.pdf&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Mixed-precision algorithms combine low- and high-precision computations in order to benefit from the performance gains of reduced-precision without sacrificing accuracy. In this work, we design mixed-precision Runge-Kutta-Chebyshev (RKC) methods, where high precision is used for accuracy, and low precision for stability. Generally speaking, RKC methods are low-order explicit schemes with a stability domain growing quadratically with the number of function evaluations. For this reason, most of the computational effort is spent on stability rather than accuracy purposes. In this paper, we show that a naïve mixed-precision implementation of any Runge-Kutta scheme can harm the convergence order of the method and limit its accuracy, and we introduce a new class of mixed-precision RKC schemes that are instead unaffected by this limiting behaviour. We present three mixed-precision schemes: a first- and a second-order RKC method, and a first-order multirate RKC scheme for multiscale problems. These schemes perform only the few function evaluations needed for accuracy (1 or 2 for first- and second-order methods respectively) in high precision, while the rest are performed in low precision. We prove that while these methods are essentially as cheap as their fully low-precision equivalent, they retain the convergence order of their high-precision counterpart. Indeed, numerical experiments confirm that these schemes are as accurate as the corresponding high-precision method.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Selected Presentations</title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/talks/2024_06_14_fenics24_oslo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/talks/2024_06_14_fenics24_oslo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-g-n-wells--download&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, G. N. Wells, &lt;em&gt;Reduced- and mixed-precision finite element kernels&lt;/em&gt;, FEniCS 2024. Simula Research Laboratory, Oslo, Norway, (2024).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/2024_06_14_FEniCS24_Oslo.pdf&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this talk we investigate the effect of rounding errors in the computation of finite element (FE) kernels&#xA;and we develop strategies for reduced- and mixed-precision acceleration using half-precision floating point formats.&#xA;Possible applications of this work include: reduced- and mixed-precision preconditioning, linear and nonlinear solvers, and timestepping methods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The popularity of artificial intelligence has pushed for the design of computer architectures that&#xA;are increasingly faster at performing computations using fewer bits. For instance, 16-bit half-precision computations&#xA;are over 32 times more efficient than double precision computations on NVIDIA H100 GPU tensor cores. However,&#xA;reducing the precision leads to a significant increase in rounding errors and extreme care must be taken during algorithmic design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/shallow_waters2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/shallow_waters2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-kloewer-s-hatfield-m-croci-p-dueben-t-palmer--article&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Kloewer, S. Hatfield, M. Croci, P. Dueben, T. Palmer, &lt;em&gt;Fluid simulations accelerated with 16 bit: Approaching 4x speedup on A64FX by squeezing ShallowWaters.jl into Float16&lt;/em&gt;, Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems (2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2021MS002684&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most Earth-system simulations run on conventional CPUs in 64-bit double precision floating-point numbers Float64, although the need for high-precision calculations in the presence of large uncertainties has been questioned. Fugaku, currently the world’s fastest supercomputer, is based on A64FX microprocessors, which also support the 16-bit low-precision format Float16. We investigate the Float16 performance on A64FX with ShallowWaters.jl, the first fluid circulation model that runs entirely with 16-bit arithmetic. The model implements techniques that address precision and dynamic range issues in 16 bit. The precision-critical time integration is augmented to include compensated summation to minimize rounding errors. Such a compensated time integration is as precise but faster than mixed-precision with 16 and 32-bit floats. As subnormals are inefficiently supported on A64FX the very limited range available in Float16 is 6.10-5 to 65504. We develop the analysis-number format Sherlogs.jl to log the arithmetic results during the simulation. The equations in ShallowWaters.jl are then systematically rescaled to fit into Float16, using 97% of the available representable numbers. Consequently, we benchmark speedups of 3.8x on A64FX with Float16. Adding a compensated time integration the speedup is 3.6x. Although ShallowWaters.jl is simplified compared to large Earth-system models, it shares essential algorithms and therefore shows that 16-bit calculations are indeed a competitive way to accelerate Earth-system simulations on available hardware.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/talks/2024-05-16_oxford_na_seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/talks/2024-05-16_oxford_na_seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci--download&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, &lt;em&gt;Multilevel Monte Carlo methods for the approximation of failure probability regions&lt;/em&gt;, Computational Mathematics and Applications Seminar, University of Oxford, UK (2024).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/2024-05-16_Oxford_NA_seminar.pdf&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we consider the problem of approximating failure regions. More specifically, given a costly computational model with random parameters and a failure condition, our objective is to determine the parameter region in which the failure condition is likely to not be satisfied. In mathematical terms, this problem can be cast as approximating the level set of a probability density function. We solve this problem by dividing it into two: 1) The design of an efficient Monte Carlo strategy for probability estimation. 2) The construction of an efficient algorithm for level-set approximation. Following this structure, this talk is comprised of two parts:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/sr_review2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/sr_review2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-m-fasi-n-j-higham-t-mary-m-mikaitis--article&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, M. Fasi, N. J. Higham, T. Mary, M. Mikaitis, &lt;em&gt;Stochastic Rounding: Implementation, Error Analysis and Applications&lt;/em&gt;, Royal Society Open Science (2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.211631&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Stochastic rounding randomly maps a real number to one of the two nearest values in a finite precision number system. First proposed for use in computer arithmetic in the 1950s, it is attracting renewed interest. If used in floating-point arithmetic in the computation of the inner product of two vectors of length n, it yields an error bounded by \sqrt(n)u with high probability, where u is the unit roundoff, which is not necessarily the case for round to nearest. A particular attraction of stochastic rounding is that, unlike round to nearest, it is immune to the phenomenon of stagnation, whereby a sequence of tiny updates to a relatively large quantity are lost. We survey stochastic rounding, covering its mathematical properties and probabilistic error analysis, its implementation, and its use in applications, including deep learning and the numerical solution of differential equations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/talks/imalesliefoxprize/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/talks/imalesliefoxprize/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci--download&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, &lt;em&gt;Mixed-precision explicit Runge-Kutta methods&lt;/em&gt;, IMA Leslie Fox Prize Event, Glasgow (2023).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/LeslieFoxPrize2023_26-06-23.pdf&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Motivated by the advent of machine learning, the last few years saw the return of hardware-supported reduced-precision computing. Computations with fewer digits are faster and more memory and energy efficient, but a careful implementation and rounding error analysis are required to ensure that sensible results can still be obtained. In this talk we focus on mixed-precision explicit Runge-Kutta (RK) methods. Mixed-precision algorithms combine low- and high-precision computations in order to benefit from the performance gains of reduced-precision while retaining good accuracy. We show that a naive mixed-precision implementation of RK schemes harms convergence and leads to error stagnation, and we present a more accurate alternative. We introduce new RK-Chebyshev schemes that only use $q\in{1,2}$ high-precision function evaluations to achieve a limiting convergence order of $O(\Delta t^{q})$, leaving the remaining evaluations in low precision. These methods are essentially as cheap as their fully low-precision equivalent and they are as accurate and (almost) as stable as their high-precision counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/stochastic_rounding2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/stochastic_rounding2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-m-b-giles--preprint-slides&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, M. B. Giles, &lt;em&gt;Effects of round-to-nearest and stochastic rounding in the numerical solution of the heat equation in low precision&lt;/em&gt;, IMA Journal of Numerical Analysis (2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.16225&#34;&gt;Preprint&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/Manchester_07-12-20.pdf&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Motivated by the advent of machine learning, the last few years saw the return of hardware-supported low-precision computing. Computations with fewer digits are faster and more memory and energy efficient, but can be extremely susceptible to rounding errors. An application that can largely benefit from the advantages of low-precision computing is the numerical solution of partial differential equations (PDEs), but a careful implementation and rounding error analysis are required to ensure that sensible results can still be obtained.&#xA;In this paper we study the accumulation of rounding errors in the solution of the heat equation, a proxy for parabolic PDEs, via Runge-Kutta finite difference methods using round-to-nearest (RtN) and stochastic rounding (SR). We demonstrate how to implement the scheme to reduce rounding errors and we derive a priori estimates for local and global rounding errors. Let u be the roundoff unit. While the worst-case local errors are O(u) with respect to the discretization parameters, the RtN and SR error behavior is substantially different. We prove that the RtN solution is discretization, initial condition and precision dependent, and always stagnates for small enough Δt. Until stagnation, the global error grows like O(u \Delta t^{-1}). In contrast, we show that the leading order errors introduced by SR are zero-mean, independent in space and mean-independent in time, making SR resilient to stagnation and rounding error accumulation. In fact, we prove that for SR the global rounding errors are only O(u\Delta t^{-1/4}) in 1D and are essentially bounded (up to logarithmic factors) in higher dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/talks/srmp2021-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/talks/srmp2021-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci--download&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, &lt;em&gt;Solving differential equations in reduced- and mixed-precision&lt;/em&gt;, Oden Institute, Yale University and Ecole Polytecnique Federale de Lausanne (2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/Oden_22-04-21.pdf&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Motivated by the advent of machine learning, the last few years saw the return of hardware-supported reduced-precision computing.&#xA;Computations with fewer digits are faster and more memory and energy efficient, but a careful implementation and rounding error&#xA;analysis are required to ensure that sensible results can still be obtained.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This talk is divided in two parts in which we focus on reduced- and mixed-precision algorithms respectively.&#xA;Reduced-precision algorithms obtain an as accurate solution as possible given the precision while avoiding catastrophic rounding error accumulation.&#xA;Mixed-precision algorithms, on the other hand, combine low- and high-precision computations in order to benefit from&#xA;the performance gains of reduced-precision while retaining good accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/mlqmc_white_noise2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/mlqmc_white_noise2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-m-b-giles-m-e-rognes-and-p-e-farrell--preprint-talk&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, M. B. Giles, M. E. Rognes, and P. E. Farrell, &lt;em&gt;Multilevel quasi Monte Carlo methods for elliptic partial differential equations driven by spatial white noise&lt;/em&gt;, SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.12099&#34;&gt;Preprint&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/siamcse19.pdf&#34;&gt;Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When solving partial differential equations driven by additive spatial white noise, the efficient sampling of white noise realizations can be challenging. In this paper we focus on the efficient sampling of white noise using quasi-random points in a finite element method and multilevel Quasi Monte Carlo (MLQMC) setting. This work is an extension of previous research on white noise sampling for MLMC.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/talks/sr2020-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/talks/sr2020-21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-and-m-b-giles--download&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci and M. B. Giles, &lt;em&gt;Solving parabolic PDEs in half precision&lt;/em&gt;, SIAM CSE 2021 and NLA Group meeting, University of Manchester (2020-2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/Manchester_07-12-20.pdf&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Motivated by the advent of machine learning, the last few years saw the return of hardware-supported low-precision computing. Computations with fewer digits are faster and more memory and energy efficient, but can be extremely susceptible to rounding errors. An application that can largely benefit from the advantages of low-precision computing is the numerical solution of partial differential equations (PDEs), but a careful implementation and rounding error analysis are required to ensure that sensible results can still be obtained.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/mlmc_qmc_brain_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/mlmc_qmc_brain_2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-v-vinje-and-m-e-rognes--preprint&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, V. Vinje and M. E. Rognes, &lt;em&gt;Fast uncertainty quantification of tracer distribution in the brain interstitial fluid with multilevel and quasi Monte Carlo&lt;/em&gt;, International Journal for Numerical Methods in Biomedical Engineering.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.02311&#34;&gt;Preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Efficient uncertainty quantification algorithms are key to understand the propagation of uncertainty &amp;ndash; from uncertain input parameters to uncertain output quantities &amp;ndash; in high resolution mathematical models of brain physiology. Advanced Monte Carlo methods such as quasi Monte Carlo (QMC) and multilevel Monte Carlo (MLMC) have the potential to dramatically improve upon standard Monte Carlo (MC) methods, but their applicability and performance in biomedical applications is underexplored. In this paper, we design and apply QMC and MLMC methods to quantify uncertainty in a convection-diffusion model of tracer transport within the brain. We show that QMC outperforms standard MC simulations when the number of random inputs is small. MLMC considerably outperforms both QMC and standard MC methods and should therefore be preferred for brain transport models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/talks/mlqmcbrain2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/talks/mlqmcbrain2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-m-b-giles-p-e-farrell-m-e-rognes-v-vinje--download&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, M. B. Giles, P. E. Farrell, M. E. Rognes, V. Vinje, &lt;em&gt;Non-nested multilevel Monte Carlo methods with applications to brain simulation&lt;/em&gt;, Oden Institute (2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/OdenPECOS_21-02-10.pdf&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This talk consists of two parts. In the first, we develop two new strategies for spatial white noise and Gaussian-Matérn field sampling that work within a non-nested multilevel (quasi) Monte Carlo (ML(Q)MC) hierarchy. In the second, we apply the techniques developed to quantify the level of uncertainty in a new stochastic model for tracer transport in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/quasi_uniform_supermeshing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/quasi_uniform_supermeshing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-and-p-e-farrell--article-preprint&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci and P. E. Farrell, &lt;em&gt;Complexity bounds on supermesh construction for quasi-uniform meshes&lt;/em&gt;, Journal of Computational Physics 414 (2020), pp. 1–7.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0021999120302333&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.11589&#34;&gt;Preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Projecting fields between different meshes commonly arises in computational physics. This operation may require a supermesh construction and in this case its computational cost is proportional to the number of cells of the supermesh n. Given any two quasi-uniform meshes of nA and nB cells respectively, we show under standard assumptions that n is proportional to nA + nB. This result substantially improves on the best currently available upper bound on n and is fundamental for the analysis of algorithms that use supermeshes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/talks/siamcse2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/talks/siamcse2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-m-b-giles-m-e-rognes-and-p-e-farrell--download&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, M. B. Giles, M. E. Rognes, and P. E. Farrell, &lt;em&gt;MLQMC Methods for Elliptic PDEs Driven by White Noise&lt;/em&gt;, SIAM CSE 2019, Spokane, USA and ICIAM 2019, Valencia, Spain.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/siamcse19.pdf&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When solving partial differential equations driven by additive spatial white noise, the efficient sampling of white noise realizations can be challenging. In this paper we focus on the efficient sampling of white noise using quasi-random points in a finite element method and multilevel Quasi Monte Carlo (MLQMC) setting. This work is an extension of previous research on white noise sampling for MLMC.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/uq_parenchymal_tracer_distribution2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/uq_parenchymal_tracer_distribution2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-v-vinje-m-e-rognes--article&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, V. Vinje, M. E. Rognes, &lt;em&gt;Uncertainty quantification of parenchymal tracer distribution using random diffusion and convective velocity fields&lt;/em&gt;, Fluids and Barriers of the CNS 16-1 (2019), pp. 1-32.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://fluidsbarrierscns.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12987-019-0152-7&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;: Influx and clearance of substances in the brain parenchyma occur by a combination of diffusion and convection, but the relative importance of thiese mechanisms is unclear.  Accurate modeling of tracer distributions in the brain relies on parameters that are partially unknown and with literature values varying up to 7 orders of magnitude. In this work, we rigorously quantified the variability of tracer enhancement in the brain resulting from uncertainty in diffusion and convection model parameters.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: In a mesh of a human brain, using the convection-diffusion-reaction equation, we simulated tracer enhancement in the brain parenchyma after intrathecal injection. Several models were tested to assess the uncertainty both in type of diffusion and velocity fields and also the importance of their magnitude. Our results were compared with experimental MRI results of tracer enhancement.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;: In models of pure diffusion, the expected amount of tracer in the gray matter reached peak value after 15 hours, while the white matter does not reach peak within 24 hours with high likelihood. Models of the glymphatic system behave qualitatively similar as the models of pure diffusion with respect to expected time to peak but display less variability. However, the expected time to peak was reduced to 11 hours when an additional directionality was prescribed for the glymphatic circulation. In a model including drainage directly from the brain parenchyma, time to peak occured after 6-8 hours for the gray matter.  Conclusion: Even when uncertainties are taken into account, we find that diffusion alone is not sufficient to explain transport of tracer deep into the white matter as seen in experimental data. A glymphatic velocity field may increase transport if a directional structure is included in the glymphatic circulation&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/efficient_white_noise2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/efficient_white_noise2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-m-b-giles-m-e-rognes-and-p-e-farrell--article-talk&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, M. B. Giles, M. E. Rognes, and P. E. Farrell, &lt;em&gt;Efficient white noise sampling and coupling for multilevel Monte Carlo with non-nested meshes&lt;/em&gt;, SIAM/ASA Journal on Uncertainty Quantification 6-4 (2018), pp. 1630-1655.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1137/18M1175239&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/mcqmc18.pdf&#34;&gt;Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When solving stochastic partial differential equations (SPDEs) driven by additive spatial white noise, the efficient sampling of white noise realizations can be challenging. Here, we present a new sampling technique that can be used to efficiently compute white noise samples in a finite element method (FEM) and multilevel Monte Carlo (MLMC) setting. The key idea is to exploit the finite element matrix assembly procedure and factorize each local mass matrix independently, hence avoiding the factorization of a large matrix. Moreover, in an MLMC framework, the white noise samples must be coupled between subsequent levels. We show how our technique can be used to enforce this coupling even in the case of nonnested mesh hierarchies. We demonstrate the efficacy of our method with numerical experiments. We observe optimal convergence rates for the finite element solution of the elliptic SPDEs of interest in 2D and 3D and we show convergence of the sampled field covariances. In an MLMC setting, a good coupling is enforced and the telescoping sum is respected.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/talks/mcqmc2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/talks/mcqmc2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-m-b-giles-m-e-rognes-and-p-e-farrell--download&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, M. B. Giles, M. E. Rognes, and P. E. Farrell, &lt;em&gt;Efficient white noise sampling and coupling for multilevel Monte Carlo&lt;/em&gt;, MCQMC 2018, Rennes, France.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://croci.github.io/slides/mcqmc18.pdf&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When solving stochastic partial differential equations (SPDEs) driven by additive spatial white noise&#xA;the efficient sampling of white noise realizations can be challenging. In this talk we present a novel&#xA;sampling technique that can be used to efficiently compute white noise samples in a finite element and&#xA;multilevel Monte Carlo (MLMC) setting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/semismooth_deflation2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/semismooth_deflation2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;p-e-farrell-m-croci-t-m-surowiec--article&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P. E. Farrell, M. Croci, T. M. Surowiec, &lt;em&gt;Deflation for semismooth equations&lt;/em&gt;, Optimization Methods and Software (2020) - Charles Broyden prize for best OMS paper in 2020.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/10556788.2019.1613655&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Variational inequalities can in general support distinct solutions. In this paper we&#xA;study an algorithm for computing distinct solutions of a variational inequality, with-&#xA;out varying the initial guess supplied to the solver. The central idea is the combi-&#xA;nation of a semismooth Newton method with a deflation operator that eliminates&#xA;known solutions from consideration. Given one root of a semismooth residual, defla-&#xA;tion constructs a new problem for which a semismooth Newton method will not con-&#xA;verge to the known root, even from the same initial guess. This enables the discovery&#xA;of other roots. We prove the effectiveness of the deflation technique under the same&#xA;assumptions that guarantee locally superlinear convergence of a semismooth New-&#xA;ton method. We demonstrate its utility on various finite- and infinite-dimensional&#xA;examples drawn from constrained optimization, game theory, economics and solid&#xA;mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/kronecker2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/kronecker2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;m-croci-j-munoz-matute--article-preprint&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Croci, J. Munoz-Matute, &lt;em&gt;Exploiting Kronecker structure in exponential integrators: Fast approximation of the action of phi-functions of matrices via quadrature&lt;/em&gt;, Journal of Computational Science (2023)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jocs.2023.101966&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2211.00696&#34;&gt;Preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this article, we propose an algorithm for approximating the action of phi-functions of matrices against vectors, which is a key operation in exponential time integrators. In particular, we consider matrices with Kronecker sum structure, which arise from problems admitting a tensor product representation. The method is based on quadrature approximations of the integral form of the phi-functions combined with a scaling and modified squaring method. Owing to the Kronecker sum representation, only actions of 1D matrix exponentials are needed at each quadrature node and assembly of the full matrix can be avoided. Additionally, we derive a priori bounds for the quadrature error, which show that, as expected by classical theory, the rate of convergence of our method is supergeometric. Guided by our analysis, we construct a fast and robust method for estimating the optimal scaling factor and number of quadrature nodes that minimizes the total cost for a prescribed error tolerance. We investigate the performance of our algorithm by solving several linear and semilinear time-dependent problems in 2D and 3D. The results show that our method is accurate and orders of magnitude faster than the current state-of-the-art.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://croci.github.io/publications/charge_separation2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://croci.github.io/publications/charge_separation2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h5 id=&#34;j-enderlein-d-sakhapov-i-gregor-m-croci-n-karedla--article-preprint&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;J. Enderlein, D. Sakhapov, I. Gregor, M. Croci, N. Karedla, &lt;em&gt;Modeling charge separation in charged nanochannels for single-molecule electrometry&lt;/em&gt;, The Journal of Chemical Physics (2022)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0074732&#34;&gt;Article&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../preprints/charge_separation2022.pdf&#34;&gt;Preprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We model the transport of electrically charged solute molecules by a laminar flow within a nanoslit microfluidic channel with electrostatic surface potential. We derive the governing convection–diffusion equation, solve it numerically, and compare it with a Taylor–Aris-like approximation, which gives excellent results for small Péclet numbers. We discuss our results in light of designing an assay that can measure simultaneously the hydrodynamic size and electric charge of single molecules by tracking their motion in such nanoslit channels with electrostatic surface potential.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
